'Incredibles 2' Has One Huge Advantage Over 'Avengers' And 'Jurassic World'
The starting shot has been fired, and thus Hollywood is off to the races for the summer season. We should have Avengers: Infinity War grosses for those Thursday previews any minute now. Conventional wisdom suggests that Avengers: Infinity War, Jurassic World: Fallen Kingdom and The Incredibles 2 will battle it out for the domestic crown. Yeah, I guess Teen Titans Go to the Movies Solo could surprise, but Deadpool 2 probably won’t be the first R-rated movie since Saving Private Ryan in 1998 to win the U.S. summer crown.

Without discounting the advantage Avengers will have via its head start and its (likely) monstrous opening weekend, the Pixar toon will have one edge over its competition. Avengers: Infinity War will be the first live-action superhero movie in less than three months, while Deadpool 2 will arrive just over three months after Black Panther. Solo: A Star Wars Story will face theater congestion from the competition and the fact that it is the third somewhat big-budget macho live-action action fantasy extravaganza in just over a month.

Pixar’s superhero action comedy will be unique unto itself when it opens on June 15. It will be, to the day, the first high-profile animated flick in six months. It will have been six months since 20th Century Fox’s Ferdinand and just under seven months since Pixar’s own Coco. There hasn’t been a major studio animated movie worth a damn (regarding box office and audience interest) for this entire year.


Not only is The Incredibles 2 an eagerly-awaited sequel to one of Pixar’s most popular films and engineered to play to kids and grown-ups in equal measures, but it will end a six-month drought for major animated flicks. Since Ferdinand, we’ve had relative non-entities like Aardman’s Early Man (which flopped so hard, with $48 million worldwide, that we’re getting a Chicken Run 2) and the barely-released Sgt. Stubby: An American Hero. Sherlock Gnomes is the year’s biggest-grossing pure animated flick, with a whopping $39m domestic and $58m worldwide.   

Fox Searchlight’s Wes Anderson flick Isle of Dogs has earned a respectable $25 million domestic, but that PG-13 dystopian fantasy is not a conventional kid-friendly animated flick. The one almost-exception to the rule is Sony’s live-action/animated Peter Rabbit, which weathered mixed reviews and eye-rolling “controversy” over its protagonist having a food allergy to leg it to $114m domestic and $310m worldwide on a $50m budget.

Maybe one reason why Peter Rabbit stuck around so long, aside from being relative pleasant, is that it was the closest thing to a kid-friendly toon. As such, The Incredibles 2, be it great, good or not-so-good, will be (relatively speaking) unique unto itself in the marketplace in a way unlike Avengers 3, Deadpool 2, Solo and Jurassic World 2.

Sony’s Spider-Man: Homecoming legged it out (even with a massive second-weekend drop) to $331 million domestic from a $117m debut partially due to being primarily the last kid-friendly live-action biggie between early July and early November. And part of why Frozen legged it to $400m from a $93m Thanksgiving debut was that there were next-to-no major animated flicks between Thanksgiving of 2013 and The LEGO Movie in early February of 2014. Moreover, most of the concurrent live-action offerings were for adults (Lone Survivor, Saving Mr. Banks, etc.) or older kids (The Hobbit: The Desolation of Smaug, Ride Along, etc.).

Now there is a difference between being the first offering in a while and being the last offering in a while, but it will still be an advantage. This summer is light in terms of big animated flicks. You’ve got The Incredibles 2 on June 15, Hotel Transylvania 3 on July 13 and Teen Titans Go to the Movies on July 27. That’s it until WB’s Smallfoot on Sept. 28.

Depending on how violent/scary Fallen Kingdom or bawdy Mamma Mia: Here We Go Again turn out to be, the kid-friendly stuff for the summer by mid-June may be limited to those animated flicks along with presumably Ant-Man and the Wasp. Coupled with violent, R-rated flicks like Equalizer 2 and The First Purge and hard(ish) PG-13 actioners like Mission: Impossible Fallout and Skyscraper, The Incredibles 2 will be one of the only family options for its entire first quarter.

If The Incredibles 2 is any good, it will both be the first kid-friendly toon in six months and have the market almost entirely to itself for its first three months in theaters. It is not hard to see a scenario where it opens big (over/under Finding Dory’s $135 million opening, since adults may be more likely to go sans kids) and then chugs along for the first month as the Elastigirl-driven story slowly pulls in more women and girls. Couple that with the scary Jurassic World, the horrific The First Purge and the brutally violent Equalizer 2 playing to older audiences, while Skyscraper plays to older kids and their parents.

By the way, if Ant-Man and the Wasp is super kid-friendly in a way that Fallout is not, well, there’s a reason the original Ant-Man snagged $180 million from a $58m debut weekend three years ago. Yes, a lot of this is “if A is C, then D” speculation. I would not remotely count out Hotel Transylvania 3, or the various PG-13 flicks as consensus picks for the back half of the summer.

If The Incredibles 2 surprises us all and goes the distance, it will be both because it is a movie folks wanted to see and because it, as a kid-friendly animated flick, stands out from the pack among the top-tier competition.

If you like what you're reading, follow @ScottMendelson on Twitter, and "like" The Ticket Booth on Facebook. Also, check out my archives for older work HERE.